<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A treatise of divine worship tending to prove that the ceremonies imposed vpon the ministers of the Gospell in England, in present controversie, are in their vse vnlawfull.</title>
            <author>Bradshaw, William, 1571-1618.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1604</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 41 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 24 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A16620</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 3528</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S120938</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99856129</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99856129</idno>
            <idno type="VID">21652</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A16620)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 21652)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1440:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A treatise of divine worship tending to prove that the ceremonies imposed vpon the ministers of the Gospell in England, in present controversie, are in their vse vnlawfull.</title>
                  <author>Bradshaw, William, 1571-1618.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>47, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Richard Schilders],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Middelburg :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1604.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>By William Bradshaw.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Union Theological Seminary (New York, N.Y.). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Customs and practices --  Controversial literature --  Puritan authors --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:21652:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:21652:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>A Treatiſe</hi> OF DIVINE WORSHIP, TENDING to prove that the Ceremonies im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed vpon the Miniſters of the Goſpell in <hi>England,</hi> in preſent contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſie, are in their vſe vnlawfull.</p>
            <p>1604.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:21652:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:21652:2"/>
            <head>A Treatiſe of Divine worship, tending to prove that the Ceremonies impoſed vpon the Miniſters of the Goſpell in <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> in preſent controverſie, are in their vſe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. I. <hi>Of divine worſhip in generall.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">D</seg>IVINE worſhip is any actio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or ſervice that is immediatlie and directlie perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med vnto God him ſelfe, whether the true God or a falſe, whether comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by divine authoritie, impoſed by humane, or aſſumed vpon our owne heads &amp; pleaſures. For in this latitude of ſenſe is divine worſhip to be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:21652:3"/>that it may comprehend vnder it both true and falſe worſhip.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Though all Actions and ſervices that Man performeth vnto Man are not partes of civill worſhip, yet every Action and Service that man perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth directly to God, is a parte of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine worſhip, and ought meerely to concerne his own glorie. It being im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible to imagine how the creature ſhould performe any ſervice, or doe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny action to the Creator him ſelfe but worſhip. For the ground of worſhip is the ſence of ſome excellent emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nencie of goodnes in the partie wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped &amp; defect and inabilitie to doe an anſwerable good to a good recea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in the partie worſhipping, for wee need not to worſhip God, if we could be as good to him as he is to vs, &amp; ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore (except we ſhould mock him) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe receaving all good from him, we are not able to doe the leaſt good vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him, all that we can doe, is to wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:21652:3"/>him, that is, to glorifie him aboue all thinges; &amp; debaſe our ſelues before him as nothing in his preſence.</p>
               <p n="3">3. All ſpeciall things therfore done in the ſervice and worſhip of God, is worſhip: and a part of that honor that is done vnto him. And what ſo ever ſpeciall thing done in divine ſervice, is not a ſpeciall honor and worſhip vnto God, muſt needes be a diſhonor and abuſe of his Maieſty, who requireth nothing but worſhip at our handes, &amp; vnto whom we can not poſſibly doe any other good.</p>
               <p n="4">4. If therefore a man ſhall doe any ſpeciall action in the ſervice of God, of which there is no vſe out of the ſame: and that action ſo done, bring no ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall honor to God; the doing of it is a profanatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the name of God. For all ſpeciall actions done in the Service of God, muſt either bring ſpeciall ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor to God, or els they muſt needes diſhonor him.</p>
               <p n="5">
                  <pb n="6" facs="tcp:21652:4"/> 5. Divine worſhip is Internal only or Externall alſo. Internall worſhip is meerely ſpirituall, &amp; performed only within the temple of mans heart, of which none are witneſſes but God &amp; a mans owne conſcience. All the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward motions of the hart directed vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God are partes of this worſhip, as faith, hope, confidence, love, feare and ioy in God, &amp;c. which are all of them diverſe actes &amp; partes of Inward wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, in every one of which God is ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nored. All which ſpring from the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion of our owne wantes, and Gods infinite excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cy and goodnes towardes vs. We need not proceed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie further in handlinge of this wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, it nothing appertayneth to our preſent purpoſe.</p>
               <p n="6">6. Externall worſhip is an expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing and ſetting forth of the Internall by outward ſignes and rites: by which as by certaine outwarde bodily ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes and colors the ſpirituall &amp; In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:21652:4"/>worſhip of God is made viſible and ſenſible to others.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. II. <hi>Of Ceremonies in generall.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THESE ſignes and rites are called Ceremonies. A Ceremonie is a corporeall advmbration of ſome hid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den thing in the mind, that it deſireth to affect others withall, in ſome effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuall maner, for by ſuch meanes as theſe, are the ſecretes of the ſoule diſcloſed and paynted out or figured to our owne and others bodily ſenſes.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Such actions properlie are cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniall, that are meere ſhadowes and ſignes exhibiting nothing but ſome ſimilitude and reſemblance of ſuch things, as man is deſirous but not able to exhibite in ſubſtance and in deede. And therefore are called co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>plements, becauſe in doing the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a man laboureth
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:21652:5"/>to ſupply that in a ſhadow, that he can not doe in ſubſtance. And hence it is that the more vnable a man is to doe that he would, the more he vſeth to ſupply his defect with ſignes and to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kens.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. III. <hi>Of Naturall Ceremonies.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>CEremonies are either Naturall or Inſtituted. Naturall ceremonies are all ſuch voluntary compoſitions &amp; geſtures of the body, as are with mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate deliberation vſed to ſhadow forth thoſe hidde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> motions, affections, and habits of the mind, that are begot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in the mind by ſome goodnes in thoſe vnto whom they are performed and done; for a man performeth no ceremonie vnto him ſelfe, but vnto o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and the ground of that ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie is in him, vnto whom it is perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:21652:5"/> 2. For example: Authoritie in an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other begetteth reverence in me. This reverence poſſeſſing and affecting my ſoule, it breedeth in me a deſire to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt it vnto the partie revere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ced, but I cannot poſſibly doe it by any other meanes, but by ſome bodily ſhadow and ſigne, wherevpon nature teacheth me to bow the body; the like may bee ſaid of lifting vp of handes, caſting vp the eyes, &amp;c. All of which kind are cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine naturall impreſſions of the ſoule made in and vpon the body, endevou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring in and by them to make her hid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den motions ſo viſible and effectuall, as they may affect our ſelues &amp; others.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Comelines and decency doth eſpecially conſiſt in the vſe of Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies of this kinde, and they haue bene ever carefullie obſerved in the Church of God, aſwell before Chriſt as ſince, both in her publique and pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate miniſtrations; which willfully to neglect, were to ſinne againſt God,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:21652:6"/>and for any to inhibite only vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their will and pleaſure, were impietie. But theſe Ceremonies in controverſie are of another nature as ſhall afterward appeare.</p>
               <p n="4">4. This firſt kind of Ceremonies the more naturall they are &amp; the more they ſhall appeare to flow from the free &amp; inforced will, of him that acteth them, the more decent and of greater grace they are, for they are ſuch ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes as are ſent forth from our paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons by the light of nature, and are not fit for any other vſe or ſignification.</p>
               <p n="5">5. And as nature only frameth them well, ſo if it ſhal appeare that they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed from her and are not forced and wrong from men <hi>(invita minerva)</hi> ſhe putteth into them ſuch a light, that any of ordinarie conceyt may in the ſigne ſee the thing ſignified.</p>
               <p n="6">6. Theſe Ceremonies though Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall and therefore common to all men, yet are they not in all degrees v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niverſally
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:21652:6"/>the ſame, becauſe havinge their originall from the naturall moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and conceptions of the minde, eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially paſſion &amp; affection, by which they are animated and formed, there being in the ſtock of mankind ſuch di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſitie of natures &amp; diſpoſitions; ſuch diverſe degrees of the ſame inclinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; ſuch a divers compoſition and minglinge of affections, it can not be but nature muſt needes vary and bee divers in them.</p>
               <p n="7">7. And though they are naturall, yet are they not ſuch as nature by vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence forceth and wringeth from men (as the actions of panting and brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinge) ſuch as men cannot at their pleaſure abſtaine from, or lay downe, for laughter in extreeme mirth, and weeping in great ſorrow, though they be naturall impreſſions and ſignes of inward and hidden paſſions, yet are they not Ceremonies; but ſuch <hi>ſignes</hi> only are ceremonies, wherein there is
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:21652:7"/>concurrence both of <hi>nature</hi> and <hi>will,</hi> in the framing and vſe of them, as appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth in the particulars aboue ſpecified; and therefore are ſuch, as may vpon ſome ſpeciall or particular occaſions, be omitted or ſuppreſſed.</p>
               <p n="8">8. Thus much of <hi>naturall</hi> ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies. Inſtituted ceremonies are ſuch outward <hi>rites</hi> and <hi>ſignes</hi> as by reaſon of ſome Analogie or ſimilitude, are or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deyned and appointed to ſignifie and ſhadow forth any <hi>mystical truth.</hi> They being not brought forth by nature to any ſuch end or purpoſe: of whiche kinde are all the Iewiſh Ceremonies, Our Sacramentes, All Paganiſh &amp; Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh rites, &amp; thoſe Ceremonies in pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent controverſie. For none of al thoſe externall rites, doe by nature ſignifie any ſuch matter, but their vſes &amp; ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifications are put vpon them only by the wil of the <hi>institutor</hi> or vſer, and are not ſo much intended for decencie &amp; order, as for <hi>ſolemnitie</hi> and <hi>ſtate.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="9">
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:21652:7"/> 9. Thoſe things that are put to this Ceremoniall vſe, being not made by nature to any ſuch end or purpoſe, muſt, if they be not vaine and fooliſh, borrow light from ſome <hi>word</hi> of <hi>insti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution,</hi> for the more <hi>mysticall</hi> the Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies of this kinde are and of ſecrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tecſenſe, of greater grace they are.</p>
               <p n="10">10. Naturall Ceremonies, if by in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution &amp; appointment they bee put to any other vſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> nature it ſelf hath fitted them vnto, doe looſe their name and become Inſtituted Ceremonies, as <hi>kneeling</hi> tied to eating and drinking in the Sacrament, &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. IIII. <hi>Of civill and</hi> religious <hi>Ceremonies in generall.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THE vſe of both theſe kindes of ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies, that is naturall and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted, is either in civill ſervices of
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:21652:8"/>man to man, or in religious ſervices of man to God from whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce ceremonies receave a ſecond denomination, and are called (whether they be natural or inſtituted) either Civill or Religious Ceremonies.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Civill Ceremonies therfore are ſuch <hi>Rites</hi> and <hi>Ceremonies,</hi> as are per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed in Civill offices and duties be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene man &amp; man, as they are mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of a civill body or incorporation. The right vſe whereof is called Civili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and the contempt <hi>rudenes;</hi> the end of civill Ceremonies is to ſignifie and ſhadow thoſe inward affections that one man deſireth to ſhew to another, in the due vſe of theſe ceremonies co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtes <hi>humanitie, lowlines, curteſie, good manners, civill ſtate and pompe, &amp;c.</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Ceremonies of this kinde are not controverted, we paſſe them by.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Religious Ceremonies are ſuch outward Rites as are perfourmed in
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:21652:8"/>religious duties and ſervices of man to God: and they are outward ſhadowes of <hi>zeale, devotion, faith, holynes, reverence of the maiestie of God, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. In the vſe of theſe Ceremonies eſpecially doth externall worſhip co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt whether true or falſe.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Religious Ceremonies are either <hi>Common</hi> or <hi>Proper:</hi> common Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies are ſuch as are equally vſed in ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill and religious matters: bowing the knee vſed in prayer, is a religious cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monie, ſignifying in that action a Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine reverence of God. Yet it is not a ceremonie peculiar and proper to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, becauſe it is a ceremonie that is and may be vſed to the Magiſtrate, to ſhadow forth alſo civill worſhip due vnto him. Of which nature all natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Ceremonies ſeeme to be, and any Inſtituted Ceremonie may bee, if it haue no reference to Religion in the vſe.</p>
               <p n="6">6. Though matters of civill order
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:21652:9"/>and decencie be very improperly cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Ceremonies, they being rather matters of ſubſtance, and it being im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pietie wilfullie and without neceſſitie to neglect them in the Congregation of <hi>Saintes,</hi> or to do any thing contrary vnto them: Yet all things te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, may for doctrine ſake be referred to this head. For though Gods wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip doe not conſiſt in them, yet Gods worſhip is profaned in the wilfull con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt &amp; neglect of them. Yea as farre forth as naturall and civill decencie &amp; comelines are outward ſhadowes of inward worſhip, They may bee ſafelie reputed partes of diuine worſhip.</p>
               <p n="7">7. Matters therfore of order and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cencie in the ſervice of God are all ſuch matters as are drawen from the ordinarie civill cuſtomes of men, and which for any to neglect wilfully, would ſeem to the reaſon of a natural man a diſorderly &amp; vnſeemely thing. As to come to the aſſembly clothed,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:21652:9"/>and that in ſeemely and uſuall ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parell, according to our civill cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings in the world, to ſit there qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etlie and in a comely manner, in reſpect of compoſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of body, to give as much as may be, vpper place to our civill ſuperiours, that the place of mecting be fair ſwept; that the Table of the Lorde in the time of Communion, bee ſpread after the civill faſhion of the Cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, with a faire table-cloth; that men pray bare-headed, &amp;c. Theſe orders vſed in civill meetinges of men, wherein civil decencie is ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved and kept, ought not to bee neglected in religious meetings, and therefore they may be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led common Ceremonies or or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders.</p>
               <p n="8">8. Theſe ceremonies of civill order and decencie, are of that na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture &amp; neceſſitie, that for the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate wilfully to inhibite, were
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:21652:10"/>ſinne in him, and for any particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar man not to vſe and obſerve as much as convenientlie hee can, (though authoritie had never en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyned them in particular) were impietie. And therefore they are of a farr different nature from the ceremonies in controverſie: For let it be ſuppoſed to bee no ſinne to vſe theſe when the Magiſtrate enioyneth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: yea ſuppoſe them to be holy ornamentes and Rites, yet if no authoritie humane or di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine had iuſtituted them, it had bene no ſinne for any man to ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glect them, nay it were a foule ſinne to vſe them. For example: Our Lords ſpirituall enioyne eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Miniſter in Divine ſervice, to weare a white linen Ephod or ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plice, they may (if it pleaſe them) as lawfully enioyne him to have painted before and behinde, two faire red croſſes: but if a private
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:21652:10"/>man vpon his owne head ſhould vſe his Surplice ſo, though it bee an honourable ſigne that he ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth, it would be made a grievous crime.</p>
               <p n="9">9. They therefore doe but gull the ſimple of the world, that from humane authoritie to inſtitute ſuch civill orders as are aboue ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified, doe inferre that man hath authoritie to bringe into the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice and worſhip of God ſuch ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies, as are cleane of another nature. As though becauſe the Magiſtrate may ordeine ſuch Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies, as without his ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, were impietie for a man not to obſerve, therefore hee may or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deyne ſuch ceremonies whiche without his ordina<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce at leaſt, were impietie and wickednes for any to vſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:21652:11"/>
               <head>CHAP. V. <hi>Of Ceremonies peculiar to Religion.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THOSE Ceremonies that are proper to Religion are ſuch as in a peculiar manner are tied to religious perſons actions and pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes only, eſpecially ſuch as are in a ſpeciall manner tied to the ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lempne worſhip of God. In theſe ceremonies conſiſtes the external forme of divine worſhip, and they are the outward badges &amp; cogni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zances of the ſame.</p>
               <p n="2">2. All Ceremonies vſed in the ſervice of God, are either civill ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies (to witt ſuch as are alſo of the ſame vſe out of the ſervice of God) or holy Ceremonies, to wit ſuch wherin holines conſiſtes in the due vſe of them; or els they
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:21652:11"/>are prophane, that is ſuch as have no vſe, or a ſuperſtitious vſe. The ceremonies in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>troverſie are not
<note n="*" place="margin">For then the bare o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſsion of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, would argue rude<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>civilitie.</note> civil ceremonies: again it is grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted there is no holynes in the vſe of them
<note n="†" place="margin">Som nigher his M. haue given it out y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he would (if he could) hang thoſe that put ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lines in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</note>, Therefore they are pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane ceremonies, and by conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent not to be mingled with ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly things.</p>
               <p n="3">3. As there are diverſities of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion and Churches, ſo there are diverſities of Rites and Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies by which they are diſtingui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, and ceremonies are the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> walles wherby (for the moſt parte) one Church is devided fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> another. For he that ſhall with a more narrow eye ſeeke into theſe things ſhall ſee, that for the moſt parte, the diverſities and varieties of Ceremonies are the begetters of diverſitie of doctrines, and opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, whereby one Religion dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fereth from another.</p>
               <p n="4">
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:21652:12"/> 4. The more one Church dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fereth from another in Rites and Ceremonies, the more it vſeth to differ in ſubſtance of doctrine; and the more one Church draweth neare vnto another in Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, the more it draweth neare vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to it in ſubſtance of doctrine. The Churches of <hi>France</hi> &amp; <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> in ſubſtance of doctrine doe ſo much the more differ from the Synagogue of <hi>Rome,</hi> by how much the farther they differ from her in Ceremonies, then other Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches; and ſome in the Church of <hi>England</hi> that doe ſtrive to come to <hi>Rome</hi> in Ceremonies, come ſo much the nearer to her in do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, as might appeare by divers inſtances if the matter were not too too apparent.</p>
               <p n="5">5. He that hates the Religion it ſelfe, hates all the ſhadowes and ſhewes of the Religion; &amp; he that
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:21652:12"/>loves the ſhadowes and rytes of a Religion, he loves the Religion it ſelf; he loves a Pope wel that loves the triple Crown; he loves a Fryer well, that dotes vpon his Cowle, and ſhaven crowne; and out of queſtion he loves a Maſprieſt with all his heart, that is mad, vpon his maſſing attire, or any part therof.</p>
               <p n="6">6. As it is rudenes and want of civilitie, to neglect or contemne a Civill Ceremonie, ſo it is propha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes &amp; irreligion to neglect or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temne a Religious Ceremonie: &amp; as outward civilitie conſiſts in the due vſe of civill Ceremonies, ſo outward holines &amp; religion con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts in the due vſe of all Religious Ceremonies: Thoſe Ceremonies therefore are prophane and not beſeeming the true worſhip of God, that are ſo far from any ſhew of holines in the vſe of them, that they make the partie that refuſeth
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:21652:13"/>the vſe of them to ſeeme, and to be reputed pure, holy, and preciſe, of which nature our Ceremonies in controverſie are.</p>
               <p n="7">7. As civill Ceremonies tend to the honor of them vnto who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> civil worſhip is due, &amp; is a part therof: So Religious Ceremonies tend to the honor of him vnto whom reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious worſhip is due and is a parte therof, neither can a man poſſibly imagine how any thing ſhould be religious whether a Subſtance or a Ceremonie, but it muſt needes re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect him that religion it ſelfe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecteth, as therefore we performe civill honor vnto thoſe vnto who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we performe civill ceremonies, ſo we performe Religious &amp; Divine honors vnto thoſe that we obey in a religious ceremonie. They ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that claime &amp; perform obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence therin, do claime &amp; perform that which is due only to God.</p>
               <p n="8">
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:21652:13"/> 8. Nothing intended or done by man is an honour to God, but that which is an obedience vnto God in ſome Commandement. All Ceremonies therefore of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion that are an honour vnto God, muſt be comma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded by God himſelfe: and to bring in ſuch Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies into his worſhip as are no honour to him, is to mocke God.</p>
               <p n="9">9. All Religious Ceremonies or Ceremonies of Religion, are ſpiritnall, that is, are ordeyned for ſpirituall vſes and endes, and not for civill or temporall, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore are outward notes and teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies of thoſe things that make vs ſpirituall men, and they are partes of ſpiritual honor due vnto ſpirituall authoritie and lordſhip.</p>
               <p n="10">10. All ſpirituall Lordes may clayme as their due, ſpiritual wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, and therefore may inſtitute
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:21652:14"/>religious Ceremonies: for looke what difference there is betweene humane and divine, Temporall &amp; Spirituall, the ſame differe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce there is betweene the peculiar worſhip due to the one, and to the other: if therefore Temporal Lords may require all civill rites and honors, Spirituall Lordes may require all Divine and Spirituall rites and honors.</p>
               <p n="11">11. Civill honor &amp; reverence onely can not nor ought not to pleaſe a <hi>Spirituall Lord,</hi> hence it is that the <hi>Spirituall Lordes</hi> of our Church ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tent them ſelues with ſuch honor that we giue to civill Magiſtrates and Princes, but we muſt obey them in peculiar re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious duties and ſervices; and ſurely it is meete that if there bee any ſuch beſides Chriſt, that we performe ſpirituall homage vnto them, and they are not worthie
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:21652:14"/>that high ſtyle that wilbe content with temporalls, when ſpiritualls are due.</p>
               <p n="12">12. Thoſe Ceremonies that are enioyned by true ſpirituall Lords, are truely ſpirituall &amp; holy, even as ſpirituall and holy as the Sacraments, though they conſiſt of ſom things in their own nature indifferent; and thoſe Lordes are not ſpirituall, that are not able by their ſole authoritie and word, to hallow that which before was not holy.</p>
               <p n="13">13. Thoſe that can make a Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plice, a Cope, a Croſſe, &amp;c. to be ornamentes of Religion and holy Ceremonies: can, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it pleaſeth them, make a ſhaven Crowne, a Monkes habit, ſpitle in Baptiſme, holy Water, the triple Crowne, &amp; all the Miſſall rytes, as holy. For they are al of the ſame nature: and thoſe that can finde no reaſon to
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:21652:15"/>prove thoſe vnholy and vnlawful, would finde none to proove anie other externall Rite to bee ſo, if they ſhould in the ſame maner be impoſed.</p>
               <p n="14">14. Thoſe that have power v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon their owne will and pleaſure to bring into Gods ſervice ſome indifferent thing, may bring in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
<note n="*" place="margin">For all indifferent thinges are of the ſame nature.</note> indifferent thinge: thoſe that may bring in without ſpecial war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant from God, pyping into his ſervice, might aſwell bringe in dauncing alſo; thoſe that haue au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie to ioyne to the ſacrament of Baptiſme the ſign of the croſſe, haue authoritie alſo (no doubt) to ioyne to the Sacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of the Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, fleſh, broth, butter or cheeſe, and worſe matters then thoſe, if they will. Yea, thoſe that have po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer to make peculiar formes of Religion &amp; worſhip, have power to make and invent a Religion &amp;
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:21652:15"/>worſhip of their owne.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VI. <hi>Of Divine worſhip in ſpeciall, and first of true worſhip.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THvs much of Divine Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip in generall, both Inward and Outward, &amp; of Ceremonies wherein Outward Worſhip eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially conſiſteth. Now lett vs in ſpeciall conſider the ſame. Divine worſhip therefore is eyther true Worſhip or falſe.</p>
               <p n="2">2. True worſhip is that imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate ſervice that the true GOD him ſelfe requireth to bee perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med vnto him ſelfe. In the exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe whereof conſiſteth true holy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and Religion.</p>
               <p n="3">3. True worſhip both for mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and manner, ought to be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the preſcript rule of
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:21652:16"/>Gods word only: neither hath a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny mortall ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> authoritie to frame according to his owne conceyte, any forme or faſhion of Gods ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice and worſhip; for the manner of worſhip alſo muſt be holy, and not the matter only; and no man hath power to make any thinge holy, that God halloweth not by his word and ſpirit.</p>
               <p n="4">4 All civill furtherances and neceſſarie circumſtances of Gods ſolemne worſhip, though they be not eſſentiall partes of the ſame, nor by ſpeciall Nomination com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded: Yet are they to bee e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteemed Ordinances of God, and not humane inventions. As God having ordayned that his Saints dwelling together both Men, Women and children, of all ſortes and degrees, ſhould ordinarilie at appointed times meet together, it muſt needs be preſuppoſed to bee
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:21652:16"/>his ordinance that they meete to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether in ſome ſuch ordinarie pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, as are fitteſt for to receive moſt commodiouſlie ſuch Aſſemblies: ſo God having ordeyned that his Miniſters ſhould preache or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clayme ſalvation to a multitude geathered together, and that they ſhould ſit at his feete, hath alſo or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deyned that the Miniſters ſeate ſhould be higher then the reſt of the peoples; and the like may bee ſaid of all other ſuch Circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of Divine worſhip, which are matters of ſo baſe and low conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration, and ſo ſubiect to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon ſence, that it neither beſemeth the maieſtie of the worde of GOD in ſpeciall, or humane authoritie de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rived fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> God, to make any lawes in particuler about them; no more then to make lawes that one ſhold not ſit in the Congregation vpon anothers lappe, or one ſpit vppon
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:21652:17"/>anothers clothes, or face: or that men ſhould not make antick faces in the Church.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VII. <hi>Of falſe worſhip.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THVS much of true worſhip. Falſe worſhip is ſuch a ſervice of God as hath no warrant from God him ſelfe: worſhip is falſe in matter or manner in whole or in parte; neither can the true matter of worſhip ſanctifie a corrupt ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, or the true manner ſanctifie a corrupt matter, or ſome partes of true worſhip, or the whole it ſelfe, ſanctifie any parte of falſe worſhip that ſhalbe adioyned to it, or min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gled with it.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Whatſoever is vnholy and ſuperſtitious out of Gods <hi>ſolemne ſervice,</hi> can not bee made by the
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:21652:17"/>ſole appointment &amp; will of man ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and good in the <hi>ſolemne ſervise</hi> of God, but muſt needes be more vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holy and ſuperſtious therein, &amp; ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore a parte of falſe worſhip. If for a man to ſigne him ſelfe or another in the forchead with the <hi>ſigne</hi> of the <hi>Croſſe</hi> out of baptiſme, be ſuperſtiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and vnholy, it can not be good in Baptiſme but a prophanerite.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The more light and toyiſh the thinges ſeeme to bee that without warrant from God are brought into the worſhip of GOD, the more wee ſhould abhorre conformitie vnto them, it being a fearfull preſumpti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, to ſerve God in a toyiſh manner: for who is he that trembles at the Maieſtie of God, that dares vſe in his worſhip any toy and trifle? They are deceaved therefore that thinke that therefore we ſhould not make ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to vſe them becauſe they are toyes.</p>
               <p n="4">
                  <pb n="34" facs="tcp:21652:18"/> 4. That is a corrupt manner of worſhip wherein there is confuſion and vndecencie, for all things muſt be done in the ſervice of God, in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cencie, order and comelines, as it is graunted; &amp; vnder the name where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of theſe ceremonies are obtruded v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon vs: But thoſe things that are vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>decent and diſorderly in other mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and of no neceſſarie vſe in Gods worſhip, can not be matters of order and decency in the ſervice of God, except God him ſelfe ſhould in a ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall maner commaund them.</p>
               <p n="5">5. It being therefore confuſion and diſorder in civil matters where a multitude ioynes together in a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon ſuite and ſupplication for all to ſpeake at once the ſame wordes: and comon wiſdome and diſcretion ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving taught it to be a decent and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly ceremonie, that ſome foreman ſhould ſpeake, and the reſt hold their peace, giving only ſome ſigne and te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimonie
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:21652:18"/>of aſſent: he muſt be more then a man, that muſt make it an or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly thing in our generall and ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narie ſuites and prayers to God, for all the congregation to open their mouthes together in a prayer, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially ſith God hath in ſpeciall ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed the Miniſter to bee the mouth of the people, and expreſſely requireth the aſſent of the people only in the word, Amen.</p>
               <p n="6">6. It being a ridiculous diſorder in other matters in any ſolemnitie, where any Deed or Record is to bee read or rehearſed for one to read one period, and another read or ſay ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, how can it by mans witt &amp; wil, without ordinance from God, bee a matter of order, for the Miniſter to read one verſe of ſcripture, and the people another; for the Miniſter to ſay one piece of a prayer, and the people by way of catch, to ſaye ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
               <p n="7">
                  <pb n="36" facs="tcp:21652:19"/> 7. If any thing be vndecent out of the worſhip of God (the ſame rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of vndeacency remayning) it is much more vndecent in the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of God; for the more excellent the thing is, in whiche an vndecent thing is vſed, the more vndecent the thing is that is ſo vſed. As if it be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>decent to goe naked in any compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie, it is much more vndecent to goe ſo in the Congregation: If fowle ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parell be every where elſe vndecent, it can not be decent in Gods ſervice, though all the Biſhops in the world ſhould decree it.</p>
               <p n="8">8. An vndecent and diſorderly thing the more ſtrictly it is vrged in the ſervice of God, the more daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous it is to yeelde vnto the ſame, &amp; ſo much the more effectuall cauſe of falſe worſhip.</p>
               <p n="9">9. If there be ſome apparell that doeth in ſpeciall maner become the ſervice of God, and deſerves to bee
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:21652:19"/>appropriated vnto it, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by the ſame poſition there muſt be ſome apparell that doeth deforme and diſgrace the ſervice and worſhip of God: for if no apparell can deforme it, then no apparell can bee an ornament or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent forme vnto it.</p>
               <p n="10">10. If any apparell doe deforme Gods true worſhip, it is that apparel, that doth moſt beautifie and grace the falſe and Idolatrous worſhip of God, As that apparell muſt needes moſt deforme a wyſe man that doth moſt adorne a foole, and that appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rell muſt needes bee moſt vnbeſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming a King, that is ſeemely and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent for a begger.</p>
               <p n="11">11. If therefore men would ſett their wittes vpon the higheſt ſtreyne to invent an apparell to diſgrace the Miniſters of the Goſpell, they could not invent a more odious attire then the conſecrated attyre of a filthy maſſe-prieſt, the moſt abhominable
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:21652:20"/>Idolater in the earth.</p>
               <p n="12">12. Thoſe that abhorre Idolatrie as much as they doe beggerie and folly, can not but hate and abhorre the badges of Idolatrie as much as the badges of folly and beggerie, and therefore can not but accompt that prieſtly attyre that is enioyned vnto vs by our Prelates, an apparell more vnbeſeeming the Miniſter of the Goſpell, then a Cloake with a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand patches, or a coate with foure ellebowes, for beggery and folly being iudgementes and not ſinnes, the notes of beggerie and folly can not be ſo odious in a ſpirituall eye, as the notes of Idolatry.</p>
               <p n="13">13. If it be denyed, that the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parell enioyned is popiſh, becauſe it was before popery was; this anſwere may be made. 1. It can never bee proved that it was before popery. For though not all popery, yet ſome
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:21652:20"/>popery was in the Apoſtles tymes: moſt of the hereſies were before the full revealing of Antechriſt which notwithſtanding wee faſten vpon them and count popiſh they having intertained them. If therefore an er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour mainteyned before Popery, &amp; retayned by Papiſtes, deſerue the name of a popiſh errour, why ſhould not vnneceſſary apparell, though v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed before, yet entertayned now on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by them, and thoſe that receaue it from them, bear the name of Popiſh attyre. 2. As a Coat of divers colours is a fooles coate, notwithſtanding that <hi>Ioſeph</hi> one of the 12. Patriarkes wore one, ſo a white linen garment is a popiſh garment though ſome Miniſters in the Eaſt Churches did weare them, and yet it can never bee proved that either they wore ſuch a one, as is preſcribed vnto vs, or that it was a miniſteriall garment and not their ordinary civill attyre,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:21652:21"/>or proper to the Miniſter only, or if al this, that it was wel done: for there being no one father that wrote ſince the Apoſtles times, but haue erred in ſome matters of Doctrine, why may they not as well erre in matters of ceremonie, if all the true Churches of God beſide our own in England, and the greateſt parte of the ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enteſt Paſtors of our owne Church, are held to erre in the generall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouncing of theſe ceremonies; why might not ſome few Miniſters in the olde Church, as well erre in inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting and vſing them?</p>
               <p n="14">14. A corrupt and ſcandalous Ceremonie in the worſhip of God is ſo much the more dangerous and ſcandalous to others, by how much the more it comes graced and coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenanced with lawfull authoritie. A corrupt ceremonie enioyned by a Heatheniſh Pagan &amp; Tyra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t vnto the Miniſters of the Goſpell living vnder
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:21652:21"/>his iuriſdiction, cannot doe ſo much ſpirituall hurt, as when it ſhalbe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired by a Chriſtian Magiſtrate, for the good conceyt of the inſtitutour and ordeinor of a religious Rite, is it that breedes ſuperſtition. Thoſe therefore whoſe ſpecial calling from God is, to edifie the ſoules of men &amp; not to deſtroy them, ought ſo much the more to avoid theſe Ceremonies they iudge &amp; know to be ſcandalous and hurtfull to the ſoules of men, by howe much the greater grace and countenance they receaue from the authoritie of man, neither can the commandement of the Magiſtrate bee a ſufficient plea at the barre of Gods iudgment ſeate for a man that by vertue or force thereof alone, hath done any action (how indifferent ſo ever in it ſelfe) that his conſcience tels him will ſcandalize his brother, and ſo hurt his ſoule; groſſe therfore is the doctrine of them that teach,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:21652:22"/>That Paule (if the Magiſtrate had commaund him) ſhould haue eaten fleſhe, though his brothers ſoule ſhould haue bene damned for it.</p>
               <p n="15">15. The more indifferent an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is in it ſelfe, the more odious it ought to be vnto vs when we ſhall perceaue it to hurte our brothers ſoule, which ought to be a thouſand times dearer vnto vs then his body, or our owne liues, for he ſhewes nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther loue nor mercy to his brother, that had rather be the inſtrument of his everlaſting damnation, then omit the doing of a meere indifferent thing, though hee ſhould incurre therefore any bodily puniſhment whatſoever. That forme therefore of Gods ſervice that conſiſts in the vſe of ſuch things indifferent, as experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence manifeſteth, are a ſcandall (and by conſequent a deſtruction) to the ſoules of infinit numbers, ought not to bee vſed of any, much leſſe of
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:21652:22"/>thoſe, who are called by Chriſt to feed the ſoules of men and not to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy them. How ſcandalous theſe Ceremonies are to all, how the omiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of them cannot be ſcandalous to any, but vnto ſuch as are worſe ſcandalized already by embracing them, requires a larger Treatiſe.</p>
               <p n="16">16. No Magiſtrate that is a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian will chalenge authoritie to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy the ſoule of any man, and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he cannot vpon his owne meere will &amp; pleaſure without ſinne againſt God, enioyne any thing (not requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by God) that evidently tendeth to the deſtruction of any mans ſoule; and thoſe ſubiects that (being ready to performe any dutie that God re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quireth vnto the Magiſtrate) ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe to doe any ſuch thing ſo requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and ſhall patiently and meekely yeeld themſelues to any puniſhment the Magiſtrate ſhall thinke good to lay vpon them without reſiſtance,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:21652:23"/>ſhall
<note n="*" place="margin">A paci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant ſuffring, when wee cannot in conſcience obey, is the beſt obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience.</note> performe more true and loyall obedience vnto his authoritie there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, then any of thoſe that ſhall yeeld obedience to any lawes of that kind enacted by never ſo good a Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate and (in ſhew) to never ſo good an end.</p>
               <p n="17">17. No ſubiect therefore can take any ſuch authoritie from the handes of the Magiſtrate, which may war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant him to doe any thing that ſhall evidently deſtroy his brother ſoule at any time, much leſſe in the ſervice &amp; worſhip of God wherin all things that are to be done, ought to tende to the edification of his ſoule in a ſpeciall maner.</p>
               <p n="18">18. It is plaine in the word of God, that the kingdome of God (that is) the ſervice and worſhip of God, ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth not in meates and drinkes, nor any ſuch externall rytes having no authoritie from God. When there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore without any commandement
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:21652:23"/>from God, ſuch external things ſhal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be brought into the ſervice of God, &amp; made the very formes of the ſame; ſuch Rytes muſt needs be falſe wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, and that forme of Gods ſervice muſt needes bee adulterate, that is made to conſiſt in ſuch thinges. For no authoritie can make that a part of Gods kingdome, that the worde of God doeth expreſly deny to be a part thereof.</p>
               <p n="19">19. Thoſe Ceremonies therefore in preſent controverſie being meerly by man brought into the worſhip of God, are by no means to be yeelded vnto, for it is in effect to make the Kingdom of God to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſiſt in meats and drinkes or in ſuch like thinges. For if man hath authoritie to make the kingdom of God conſiſt in ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parel, &amp;c. he hath alſo authoritie, if it pleaſe him, to make it conſiſt in ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting and drinking, &amp; may make them a part of the Liturgie aſwel as any of
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:21652:24"/>thoſe things that are in controverſie.</p>
               <p n="20">20. Thoſe peculiar Rites and Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies which are in that maner &amp; forme vſed in the ſervice of God, that if God himſelf did but ratifie &amp; confirme that preſent ſſe of them ſhould then be parts of his true out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward worſhip; muſt needs as they are vſed (without Gods ordinance) be partes of a falſe outwarde worſhip: But our ſurplices, croſſes, kneeling at the Lordes Supper, &amp;c. are ſuch, that if God ſhould but command to vſe them as we vſe them, that is if hee ſhould require every Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter in divine ſervice to weare a ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plice to note ioy, dignitie or ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, or in Baptiſme to croſſe a child in ſigne, &amp;c. Nay though he ſhould ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe no vſe at all, but barely en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyne the things the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelves to be vſed in his ſervice, yet they ſhould bee partes of Gods true outward wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, for whatſoever God tieth in a
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:21652:24"/>peculiar maner to his worſhip, is a parte thereof. Theſe Ceremonies therfore in controverſie having ſuch a vſe in the ſervice of God, vnto which they are peculiarly tied, muſt needes be vſed as partes of Divine worſhip, for elſe the bare ratifying of their preſent vſe, could not make them true worſhip; Being therefore (as they are vſed) partes of divine worſhip and not parts of true divine worſhip, becauſe not commanded of God; they are partes of falſe divine worſhip, for that divine wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip that is not true wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, is falſe wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
